<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.0.1">
<!ENTITY manrevision "0.1">
<!ENTITY date "November 2010">
<!ENTITY app "<application>&appname;</application>">
<!ENTITY appname "mp3splt-gtk">
]>
<article id="index" lang="es">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>mp3splt-gtk Manual</title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>
	mp3splt-gtk.
      </para>
      <para>Una herramienta que permite cortar sin pérdida de archivos MP3 o Ogg Vorbis. Esto significa que los cuadros seleccionados de audio o paquetes se extraen, sin necesidad de volver a codificar el archivo - que perdería calidad.</para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2010</year>
      <holder>Gunter Königsmann</holder>
    </copyright>
    <!-- translators: uncomment this:
	 
	 <copyright>
	 <year>2010</year>
	 <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
	 </copyright>
	 
    -->
    
    <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
  <para>Se concede permiso para copiar, distribuir y / o modificar este documento bajo los términos de la GNU Free Documentation License (GFDL), Versión 1.1 o cualquier versión posterior publicada por la Free Software Foundation, sin Secciones Invariantes ni Textos de Cubierta Delantera y No Volver Textos de Cubierta. Puede encontrar una copia de la GFDL en este <ulink url="ghelp:fdl"> enlace </ulink> o en el archivo COPYING-DOCS distribuido con este manual.</para>
  <para>Este manual es parte de una colección de manuales de GNOME distribuido bajo la licencia GFDL. Si desea distribuir este manual por separado de la colección, puede hacerlo añadiendo una copia de la licencia al manual, como se describe en la sección 6 de la licencia.</para>
  <para>Muchos de los nombres utilizados por las empresas para distinguir sus productos y servicios se consideran marcas comerciales. Cuando estos nombres aparecen en la documentación de GNOME, y los miembros del Proyecto de documentación de GNOME están al corriente de esas marcas, los nombres están en mayúsculas o con letra inicial mayúscula.</para>
  <para>DOCUMENTO Y VERSIONES MODIFICADO DEL DOCUMENTO SE ESTABLECEN EN LOS TÉRMINOS DE LA LICENCIA Documentación Libre de GNU CON LA QUE: <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>DOCUMENTO SE PROPORCIONAN "TAL CUAL", SIN GARANTÍA DE NINGÚN TIPO, YA SEA EXPRESA O IMPLÍCITA, INCLUYENDO, SIN LIMITACIÓN, LAS GARANTÍAS QUE LA VERSIÓN DE DOCUMENTO O MODIFICACIÓN DEL DOCUMENTO ES LIBRE DE DEFECTOS COMERCIALES, ADECUADOS PARA UN PROPÓSITO PARTICULAR O NO -INFRACCIÓN. EL RIESGO EN CUANTO A LA CALIDAD, LA PRECISIÓN Y EJECUCIÓN DEL DOCUMENTO O VERSIÓN MODIFICADA DEL DOCUMENTO ES CON USTED. SI CUALQUIER DOCUMENTO O VERSIÓN MODIFICADA PROVE DEFECTUOSO EN NINGÚN ASPECTO, USTED (NO INICIAL DEL ESCRITOR, AUTOR O CONTRIBUYENTE) ASUMIR EL COSTO DE CUALQUIER servicio, reparación o corrección. LA RENUNCIA DE GARANTÍA ES UNA PARTE ESENCIAL DE ESTA LICENCIA. NO USO DE CUALQUIER DOCUMENTO O VERSIÓN MODIFICADA DE LA PRESENTE DOCUMENTO SE AUTORIZA A EXCEPCIÓN DE CONFORMIDAD CON LA RENUNCIA; Y</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>BAJO NINGUNA CIRCUNSTANCIA Y BAJO NINGUNA TEORÍA LEGAL, YA SEA EN AGRAVIO (INCLUYENDO NEGLIGENCIA), CONTRATO, O DE OTRA MANERA, EL AUTOR, EL ESCRITOR INICIAL DE APORTACIONES, O CUALQUIER DISTRIBUIDOR DEL DOCUMENTO O VERSIÓN MODIFICADA DEL DOCUMENTO O CUALQUIER PROVEEDOR DE CUALQUIER DE ESAS PARTES, SERÁ RESPONSABLE DE CUALQUIER PERSONA POR DAÑOS DIRECTOS, INDIRECTOS, ESPECIALES, INCIDENTALES O DERIVADOS DE CUALQUIER TIPO, INCLUYENDO, SIN LIMITACIONES, DAÑOS POR PÉRDIDA DE BUENA VOLUNTAD, TRABAJO, NO O MAL FUNCIONAMIENTO, O CUALQUIER OTRO DAÑO O DERIVADO DE O EN RELACIÓN CON EL USO DEL DOCUMENTO Y VERSIONES DE MODIFICAR EL DOCUMENTO, AUN CUANDO DICHA PARTE HAYA SIDO INFORMADO DE LA POSIBILIDAD DE TALES DAÑOS.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist></para>
</legalnotice>

 
  <author role="maintainer">
    <firstname> 
      Gunter
    </firstname> 
    <surname>
      Königsmann
    </surname>
  </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>mp3splt-gtk Manual 0.1</revnumber>
        <date>2010-11-16</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1 id="mp3splt_gtk-introduction">
    <title>Introducción</title>
    <para>La <application> Mp3Splt-gtk </application> aplicación es una herramienta que permite cortar archivos MP3 y Ogg Vorbis, sin la necesidad de volver a codificar (que perdería su calidad).</para>
    <para>Las características incluyen la selección gráfica de los puntos de división, división automática de grabaciones musicales en las pistas y el ajuste automático de los puntos de división a caer en las pausas.</para>
    <figure id="Player-fig2">
      <title>mp3splt-gtk directly after startup</title>
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="figures/mp3splt-gtk.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Shows <application>mp3splt-gtk</application> directly after startup.</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <sect2 id="audiorec-tostartapp">
      <title>Starting mp3splt-gtk</title>
      <para>Usted puede comenzar <application> Mp3Splt-gtk </application> en - al menos - de las siguientes maneras:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Sound and
	    Video</guimenu><guimenuitem>mp3splt-gtk</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
	    from the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu.
	  </para> 
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Ejecutar <command> Mp3Splt-gtk </command> en el indicador en un terminal como <application> gnome-terminal </application> , O de la <application> Ejecutar una aplicación </application> diálogo.</para> 
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-closeapp">
      <title>Closing mp3splt-gtk</title>
      <para>To close the <application>mp3splt-gtk</application> window
      there are many options, too:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    choose
	    <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    press
	    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>W</keycap></keycombo>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>pulse sobre el botón en forma de X el gestor de ventanas de su elección le proporciona</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt-features">
      <title>mp3splt-gtk Features</title>
      <para>
	<application>mp3splt-gtk</application> will allow you to
	manipulate audio files without loosing any quality.
      </para>
      <para>
	This program was designed with usability in Mind and contains the
	followning features
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>La capacidad de utilizar su aplicación favorita de reproducción de audio para la reproducción del archivo que se va a cortar.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Detección automática de los lugares correctos para dividir.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Ajuste automático de puntos de división manualmente a caer en una pausa en las cercanías - que permite al usuario trabajar con menos de milisegundo precisión al especificar los puntos de división.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Importación de splitpoints para un álbum de una base de datos conocida como freedb.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Divide automáticamente álbumes que se han unido albumwrap mp3wrap o en los archivos originales.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para> 
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="mp3splt_gtk-BasicWorkflow">
    <title>Basic Workflow</title>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-OpenFile">
      <title>Opening a file</title>
      <para>
	Just press the <guibutton> Choose </guibutton> button and
	select a file to open.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-SetSplitPoints">
      <title>Choose the right split points</title>
      <sect3 id="mp3splt_gtk-SetSplitPointsManually">
	<title>Choosing split points manually</title>
	<para>
	  Press the <guibutton> Play </guibutton> button (a gray
	  triangle pointing to the right) on the
	  <guilabel>Player</guilabel> tab, listen to the music and press
	  the <guibutton>add</guibutton> button (which is on the
	  <guilabel>Player</guilabel> tab, too) every time a new audio
	  track should begin.
	</para>
	<para>
	  If you don't want to be made to press the button exactly at
	  the right centisecond the <guibutton>add</guibutton>
	  Preferences tab gives you the possibility to let the program
	  fine-tune the split points you choose.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="mp3splt_gtk-SetSplitPointsAutomatically">
	<title>Automatical setting of split points</title>
	<para>
	  The <guilabel>Type of Split</guilabel> tab provides you with
	  a wide choices of ways to select where to split a file into
	  tracks. If you want to split a media into tracks others
	  might have had access to before you can try searching for
	  splitpoint readymades in the <guilabel>FreeDB</guilabel> tab
	  instead.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-TrackInfos">
      <title>Tweaking split points and entering track information</title>
      <para>
	  The <guilabel>Splitpoints</guilabel> tab now contains a list
	  of points where tracks start or end. It also contains the
	  information if this piece of the audio file is to be kept
	  and how the corresponding track has to be named.
      </para>
      <figure id="Splitpoints">
	<title>The split point tab</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/Tracklist.png" format="PNG"/>
	    </imageobject>
	    <textobject>
	      <phrase>Shows all split points and track names.</phrase>
	    </textobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>
	If you want to change the start or end position of a track
	or give it a name just do it at any time you want.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-TrackExport">
      <title>Exporting the tracks</title>
      <para>
	  Now press the button with the green <guibutton>check
	  mark</guibutton> that is always visible in the menu
	  line. mp3splt-gtk will output all tracks into single files. If
	  anything goes wrong don't despair: Since one of the goals of
	  mp3splt-gtk is to work completely lossless even if anything
	  goes wrong not much is lost.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="mp3splt_gtk-BatchProcessing">
    <title>Batch processing of files</title>
    <para>
      Besides manual and automatic splitting of a single file
      mp3splt-gtk also supports automatic batch-processing of multiple
      files at once.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-BatchProcessingEnable">
      <title>Enabling batch processing mode</title>
      <para>Go to the <guilabel>Type of split</guilabel> tab and there
      to the <guilabel>File mode</guilabel> tab. After selecting
      <guilabel>Batch processing</guilabel> here batch processing mode
      is enabled</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-BatchProcessingModeSet">
      <title>Adding files in batch processing mode</title>
      <para>
	Go to the <guilabel>Type of split</guilabel> tab and there
	to the <guilabel>Split mode</guilabel> tab and select after
	which criteria you want the files to be split.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-BatchProcessingFileAdd">
      <title>Adding files in batch processing mode</title>
      <para>Go to the <guilabel>Batch Processing</guilabel> tab and
      add all files you want to be automatically processed.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-TrackExportII">
      <title>Exporting the tracks</title>
      <para>
	Now press the button with the green <guibutton>check
	mark</guibutton> that is always visible in the menu
	line. mp3splt-gtk will output all tracks into single files. If
	anything goes wrong don't despair: Since one of the goals of
	mp3splt-gtk is to work completely lossless even if anything
	goes wrong not much is lost.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="mp3splt_gtk-SaveResume">
    <title>Saving and resuming your work</title>
    <para>      
	mp3splt-gtk contains an export feature that saves the current
	project's state as a cue file. This cue file can later be
	re-opened by mp3splt-gtk or be used by any cd burner or other
	application that can read cue files. 
    </para>      
    <para>      
      If the cue file is used in a different application than
      mp3splt-gtk there is one feature that most probably won't work,
      though: 
    </para>
    <para>      
      The cue standard does provide commentary fields that allow
      applications to store private data (which we use for to remember
      which part of the file is not to be output).
      But since there is no standartized way to exclude parts of a
      file from the CD burning process other applications most
      probably won't know if you want to do so.
    </para>
    <para>
      To export the current split points as a cue file press
      <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export
      Splitpoints</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="mp3splt_gtk-Troubleshooting">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-PlayerWontStart">
      <title>The player won't start</title>
      <para>
	If the player won't start even if the play button is pressed try
	starting the player independently from mp3splt-gtk and pressing
	play thereafter.
      </para>
      <para>
	mp3splt-gtk knows how to remote-control SnackAmp and Audacious to
	automatically switch to the file that is about to be split.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-SplittingDoesntWork">
      <title>Splitting doesn't work</title>
      <para>
	Try to make sure that the version of libmp3splt is installed
	correspondends to the version of mp3splt-gtk.
	Even if (for newer versions of the program) the configure
	script makes sure that both versions match it might still
	be possible to have the wrong combination of these elements
	installed on the same system.
      </para>
      <para>
	If that is the case make sure that in the <guilabel>File
	mode</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Type of split</guilabel>
	tab <guilabel>Single file</guilabel> mode is selected.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-SplittingDoesntWorkII">
      <title>Splitting a certain Ogg file doesn't work</title>
      <para>
	Next to the lossy ogg vorbis format that gives good
	compression while keeping file sizes extremely low there are
	other file formats that can be kept inside an ogg container as
	well, notably ogg flac. 
      </para>
      <para>
	Flac is a completely lossless codec which means that the
	output files are sonewhat larger than Ogg vorbis ones but
	these files can be cut on any information without loosing any
	quality.
      </para>
      <para>
	Since there is no direct need mp3splt-gtk still does not
	support cutting flac files.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="mp3splt_gtk-AddingFilesDoesntWork">
      <title>Adding a file to the files view doesn't work</title>
      <para>
	Make sure that in the <guilabel>File mode</guilabel> tab of
	the <guilabel>Type of split</guilabel> tab
	<guilabel>Batch processing</guilabel> mode is selected.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>
